Finding Aid for Henry Simmons Frieze Papers 1835-1920
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Simmons Frieze Papers 1835-1920
Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.
Professor of Latin and acting president of University of Michigan. Correspondence, 1855-1856, to his wife, describing his travels and experiences in Europe; also material pertaining to affairs of University of Michigan, including letters from Andrew D. White of Cornell University; biographical and genealogical material on Frieze, eighteen volumes of records of European travel; and photographs.
851370 Aa 2; UAx; UAm
1.3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Graduate Library (donor no. 1278 ) in 1944. The typed copies of Frieze's diaries were given to the library by Orma Fitch Butler (donor no. 15 ) in 1936.
The collection is open for research.
Henry Simmons Frieze was born in Boston on September 15, 1817. He was educated at Brown University where he supported himself through his skills as an organist. Upon graduation in 1841, Frieze served as an instructor at Brown University and its grammar school. In 1854, Frieze was called to succeed Professor Haven as professor of Latin language and literature of the University of Michigan.
In 1869, Frieze was selected acting president of the University serving until 1871 when James B. Angell took office. During this period, women were first admitted to the university. Also while acting president, Frieze worked to improve the connection between the university and the high schools of the state through the establishment of the diploma system whereby schools that had been approved by a faculty committee could send students with diplomas for admission without examination.
Frieze also served as acting president on two other occasions when Angell was involved in diplomatic assignments from June 1880 to February 1882 and from October 1887 to January 1888. During the earlier of these periods, the university established schools of political science and mechanical engineering and also a professorship of music leading eventually to the formation of the University School of Music.
Frieze died December 7, 1889.
The Frieze papers are an accumulation of various personal and professional materials, including correspondence, travel diaries and letters home written while traveling in Europe, 1855-1856 and 1872-1873; miscellaneous lectures and essays; papers from his years at Brown as a student and as an instructor of Latin; various papers on his views of university education and his ideas for curriculum improvements; and photographs.
Subjects:
Cornell University.; Europe--Description and travel.; Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Travelers.; University of Michigan. Chemical Laboratory.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Classical Studies.; University of Michigan. President.; Voyages and travels.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Cemeteries.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Cemeteries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Frieze Memorial Organ.; Interiors.; Organs.; Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Tombs and sepulchral monuments.; University Hall (University of Michigan); Washtenaw Avenue (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Boise, James Robinson, 1815-1895.; Brooks, Phillips, 1835-1893.; Bröunnow, F. (Franz), 1821-1891.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Cutcheon, Byron M., 1836-1908.; Douglas, Silas H. (Silas Hamilton), 1816-1890.; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881.; Harris, Samuel Smith, 1841-1888.; Haven, E. O. (Erastus Otis), 1820-1881.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.; Rogers, Randolph, 1825-1892.; Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906.; Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.; Tappan, Julia Livingston.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Williams, George Palmer, 1802-1881.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Daguerreotypes.
- Correspondence and other papers
  - 1845-1920 (Box 1)
    (folders 1-9)
  - Letters from James B. Angell to the Frieze family (Box 1)
    (folder 9-a)
  - Letters from Lois T. Angell to Carrie Frieze 1881 (Box 1)
    (folder 9-b)
  - Letters from A.D. White 1880-1881 (Box 1)
    (photocopies; originals at Cornell University)
    (folder 9-c)
- Travels
  - Diary and jotting books of European trip 1855-1856, 15 notebooks (Box 1)
    (folder 18; notebooks no. 1-15)
  - Typescript of diary and jotting books of European trip 1855-1856, 2 volumes (Box 1)
    (typescript made in 1919 when originals were still in family possession)
    (folders 10-11)
  - Pictures and memorabilia of European trip 1855-1856, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (folders 29-30)
  - Diary of European trip with historical notes 1872-1873 (Box 1)
    (folder 12)
  - Sketch book of Italy (Box 1)
    (folder 25)
- Writings, lectures, etc
  - Address at Brown University 1841 (Box 1)
    (folder 13)
  - Lecture notes undated (Box 1)
    (folder 14)
  - Papers entitled, "The reading of the Scriptures" and "The future of Christianity" undated (Box 1)
    (folder 15)
  - Essay: "French's statue of Gen. Cass" (Box 1)
    (folder 16)
  - Draft of essay re cartoons (Box 1)
    (folder 17)
  - College essays 1838-1841 (Box 1)
    (folder 20)
- Brown University
  - Report concerning Frieze's service to Brown (Box 1)
    (folder 21)
  - Minutes of Brown Music Group (Box 1)
    (folder 26)
  - College financial statements 1838, 1839, 1941 (Box 1)
    (folder 27)
  - Catalogs of Brown University 1842-1843, 1846-1847 (Box 1)
    (folder 28)
- Miscellaneous
  - Biographical and genealogical material (Box 1)
    (folder 22)
  - re courses of study in the fine arts (Box 1)
    (folder 23)
  - Draft of plan of studies and examinations for advanced students (Box 1)
    (folder 24)
  - Date book 1854 (Box 1)
    (folder 31)
  - Frieze's copy of C. Plini Secundi Naturalis Historiae (Box 2)
    (with Frieze's marginal notes)
- Visual Materials
  Portraits; photograph of Frieze home on Washtenaw Avenue in Ann Arbor, Michigan; interior photograph of University Hall showing the Frieze Memorial Organ, and interior photograph of classroom in which Frieze taught; and photographs of Frieze's tombstone.
  - Album of University of Michigan faculty (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    see also oversize folder UAm and UAx photos
    - Portraits of Frieze, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      (photographs of Frieze's home on Washtenaw Ave.; his recitation room at the university; and his cenotaph)
Selective index to correspondents
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
1890 and folder 9-a
Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.
Feb. 2, 1888, Feb. 11, 1888
Boise, James Robinson, 1815-1895.
Jan. 2, 1856, Apr. 29, 1856, Nov. 5, 1871, Apr. 25, 1881, Nov. 9, 1881, Nov. 7, 1882, Mar. 6, 1885, Apr. 17, 1887, 1888
Brooks, Phillips, 1835-1893.
Oct. 28, 1881, Oct. 9, 1884
Brðunnow, F. (Franz), 1821-1891.
Feb. 1856
Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.
1881
Cutcheon, Byron M., 1836-1908.
Feb. 14, 1885
Douglas, Silas H. (Silas Hamilton), 1816-1890.
Nov. 7, 1881
Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881.
June 21, 1880
Harris, Samuel Smith, 1841-1888.
1880-1884 throughout
Haven, E. O. (Erastus Otis), 1820-1881.
Mar. 19, 1881
Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.
Mar. 12, 1881
Rogers, Randolph, 1825-1892.
Oct. 11, 1857, Aug. 17, 1866, Feb. 6, 1869
Schurz, Carl, 1829-1906.
Apr. 5, 1881
Tappan, Julia Livingston.
Nov. 28, 1882, Jan. 1883
Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.
1881, 1888
White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.
Throughout